<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anglo-Judæus, or The history of the Jews, whilst here in England. Relating their manners, carriage, and usage, from their admission by William the Conqueror, to their banishment. Occasioned by a book, written to His Highness, the Lord Protector (with a declaration to the Commonwealth of England) for their re-admission, by Rabbi Menasses Ben Israel. To which is also subjoyned a particular answer, by W.H.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03712</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 12254625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.863[3]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 482.b.3[8]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99882723</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99882723</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B1:3[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anglo-Judæus, or The history of the Jews, whilst here in England. Relating their manners, carriage, and usage, from their admission by William the Conqueror, to their banishment. Occasioned by a book, written to His Highness, the Lord Protector (with a declaration to the Commonwealth of England) for their re-admission, by Rabbi Menasses Ben Israel. To which is also subjoyned a particular answer, by W.H.</title>
                  <author>Hughes, William, of Gray's Inn. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.N. for Thomas Heath, in Russel-street, near the Piazza's in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: W.H. (i.e., William Hughes, of Gray's Inn).</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing M373 on UMI microfilm set "Early English books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 8.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Manasseh ben Israel. To His Highness the Lord Protector.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657. --  To His Highness the Lord Protector.</term>
               <term>Jews --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANGLO-J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DÆ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> OR THE HISTORY OF THE JEWS, Whilſt here in ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Relating their Manners, Carriage, and Uſage, from their Admiſſion By <hi>Willian</hi> the Conqueror, to their BANISHMENT.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by a Book, Written to His Highneſs, the Lord Protector (with a <hi>Declaration</hi> to the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi>) for their Re-admiſſion,</p>
            <p>By Rabbi <hi>Menaſſes Ben Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is alſo ſubjoyned a particular Anſwer, by <hi>W. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſtin de Civir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Dei, Lib. 22. Cap. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quiſquis adhuc prodigia, ut credat, requirit, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium, qui mundo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente non credit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Heath,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet,</hi> near the <hi>Piazza</hi>'s in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183674:2"/>
            <head>To His Highneſs the Lord Protector Of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Had a while ago, an opportunity to meet with a Book come abroad in print, written to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (with a Declaration to the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi>) by Rabbi <hi>Menaſſes b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Iſrael.</hi> Looking upon it, I eaſily diſcovered the ſcope thereof, but made way to upon falſe grounds and reaſons (as I conceived) altogether diſſonant to experience and truth. This perſwaſion was wrought, by reaſon of my having had ſometimes occaſion to read ſuch Authors as hold out unto us the behavior of the Jews, whilſt here formerly reſiding; which ſeemed to be ſuch, as the Engliſh Nation believed other things of them then Profitableneſs and Faithfulneſs, having bought their experience at a very dear rate. Upon a meer ſerious review and conſideration, this opinion could not but be confirmed; whereby the Rabbi appears either to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignorant of our Hiſtories (though a learned man),
<pb facs="tcp:183674:3"/>or elſe wittingly paſs by, and deny that which they clearly and fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thfully enough make out unto us. And upon a religious conſideration are his motives and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments the more impertinent; eſpecially at this time, when we ſtand leaſt in need of their Religion to come amongſt us; too many having already taken up, if not their opinions, yet ſuch as border near upon their hold. Your Highneſs hath not been ſo eaſie to be allured by his great pretences, as he might hope, and others idly, and (upon falſe and preſumptuous grounds) unworthily ſurmiſe, taking care leſt their reduction might prove dangerous to Religion, or the wealth and intereſt of the people. But (to detain your Highneſs no longer with need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs words) what is here written in anſwer to him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated calmly (which is all I can ſpeak in behalf of this Treatiſe) I humbly lay at your Highneſs feet, being ever</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſs's moſt humble and devoted Servant. W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183674:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anglo-Judaus.</hi> Or the Hiſtory of the Jews whilſt here in <hi>Endland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Jews being a people favoured eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by God, and choſen by him above all others, on whom to ſhew his grace, and in them on all mankinde, have yet in all ages ſhewn abundance of ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; for which, ſeveral ways and times they have been ſcourged: No ſooner were they freed from the Egyptian bondage, but preſently for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the mercies received,<note place="margin">Exod. 16. Numb 20.</note> and the miſeries lately ſuffered, they murmure againſt their deliverer; and being ſettled in the Land of Promiſe, eaſily forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting how they came thither, change their God, and worſhip thoſe Idols, which were not able to deliver the former Inhabitants from their Invaſion.</p>
            <p>Then quarrelling againſt the diſpenſations of God,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 1 &amp; 2 Kings.</note> they deſire the Government of Kings; under whom whilſt they lived, partly by their own depraved blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, partly by their Princes carnal Policies, they were ſtill drawn in their Religion and Manners, after the cuſtoms of the Heathen; to whom, after ſome few hundreds of years, they were left to be ſubjected and inthralled.</p>
            <p>And, though after the Babyloniſh captivity, they were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183674:4"/>not found guilty of ſo groſs Idolatry as formerly; yet ere long, they fell off from the purity of Religion, and the inwards of it,<note place="margin">Sadduciſin. Phariſaiſm.</note> to that Corruption and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which made way for that miſt of Error; which, overſpreading their mindes, and poſſeſſing their ſpirits, kept out that light, which in the fulneſs of time clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhone amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Many have been the ways, many the inſtruments, by which God hath plagued their diſobedience. The carkaſſes of the rebellious ones fell in the wilderneſſe; the Nations were part preſerved to be as thorns in their eyes, and goads in their ſides: And after the death of <hi>Solomon, Iſrael</hi> began to be againſt himſelf, and did not only ſtruggle with <hi>Eſau</hi> after ſome 130. years from the rooting out of the ten Tribes by <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manaſſer:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 &amp; 2 Kings.</note> after many inroads made by the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Egyptians and Syrians; <hi>Judah</hi> is alſo carried away into Captivity, the City deſtroyed, the Temple burnt, and nothing left of the face of a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Neither did afflictions from Forreign invaſions and captivities ceaſe after their reduction, though they were not clean removed from their Land. For what multitudes were enthralled in their ancient houſe of bondage! One hundred and twenty thouſand being reported to have been ſet at liberty by <hi>Ptolomy Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphus,</hi> at ſuch time as erecting his renowned Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he ſent for the Law of God, and 72.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſephus,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riq. lib. 12.</note> Interpreters to tranſlate it. How did <hi>Ptolomy Philopator</hi> or <hi>Phyſcon</hi> prophane the Temple? and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering many thouſands of them together, intended by ſubjecting them to the teeth of Elephants, to feed his cruel and malitious humor? And what they endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Syrian and Aſian Kingdoms, eſpecially
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183674:4"/>under <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> that vile perſon, the book of <hi>Maccabees,</hi> with other Hiſtories ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; beſides what tumults, broils, ſeditions and ſlaughters aroſe, through the ambitious tranſactions of themſelves for the Prieſthood, and royal dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity?</p>
            <p>And the Scepter was departed from <hi>Judah</hi> when <hi>Shiloh</hi> came; falling out amongſt themſelves, they were ſubjected to a Forreign power, called in to help.<note place="margin">Joſephus.</note> Great <hi>Pompey</hi> had reduced that Kingdom to <hi>Roman</hi> obedience: aliens were placed over them;<note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> the great was haraſſing them with his Tyrannies and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, when Chriſt came; who by the ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God eſcaped his hands: whileſt they reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Government of Chriſt, they were ſtill under the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyrannie; maintained partly by <hi>Herods</hi> off-ſpring, partly by others ſent from <hi>Rome:</hi> cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Lord of Life, rejecting the Goſpel of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, they were ſpued up by their own land into all Countreys, deſpiſed by all, and hated by moſt.</p>
            <p>The deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> foretold by Chriſt ſome fourty years before (whoſe blood they had char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon themſelves and poſterity) came to paſs in the days of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> the Emperor by <hi>Titus</hi> his Son;<note place="margin">Joſephus <hi>lib. 7.</hi> de bell<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Judai<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who being for the eſpecial ſweetneſs of diſpoſition, the love and delight of mankinde, was yet their overthrow, but that occaſioned by their own ſtubborneſs. Great was the concourſe of people at that time, out of reſpect to the ſeaſon; their Superſtition diſarming themſelves, put a ſtrong weapon in to the hands of the enemy; that City came the ſecond time to deſolation, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire, together with its ornament the Temple; ſome few pillars only left to poſterity,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183674:5"/>to teſtifie the ſtatelineſs of what had been.</p>
            <p>Of the remnant of this people,<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> few were left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in their own Countrey; eleven hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand periſhed in the Siege, and ninety ſeven thouſand were taken Captives: they being ſcattered abroad in divers Countreys, yet eſpecially abounded in <hi>Egypt, Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> where after ſome fifty years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, they begin to commit outrages in an unheard of manner;<note place="margin">Dion <hi>lib.</hi> 9.8.</note> here 200000 there 250000 are butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them; they eat their fleſh, beſmear themſelves with their blood, wear their skins, ſaw them aſunder, caſt them to beaſts, make them kill one another. The Emperor <hi>Trajan</hi> wondering, and ſcarce believing ſuch horrid treachery, proſecutes them as ſo many Monſters and enemies of mankinde; an infinite number are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up as a parentation.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill they cannot reſt.<note place="margin">Dion <hi>lib.</hi> 69.</note> In his Succeſſor <hi>Adrians</hi> days they muſt up again and try their fortune. That Prince had built a new City where their <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtood, and called it after himſelf <hi>Aelia,</hi> ſetting up a Sow over the gates thereof, in oppoſition to them; giving free liberty to all Nations for the exerciſe of their Religion; ſuch injuries offered to their Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as they cannot digeſt: whilſt he remains amongſt them they murmure; being gone, break out into open rebellion; joyn battel with one of the moſt expert Captains in his time;<note place="margin">Julius Severus.</note> which brings a bloody victory to the adverſary, and a fearful ſlaughter to themſelves.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that remained,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joan: vaſaeus,</hi> Chron. Hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. Anno 137.</note> 
               <hi>Adrian</hi> tranſports into <hi>Spain,</hi> his own Countrey; and thence, or from elſewhere we have nothing conſiderable of them, until the decay of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.<note place="margin">Papirius Naſ. ſenus, <hi>lib. 1.</hi>
               </note> At laſt it comes to that paſs, that Chriſtians ſelling Church-livings for money; the Jews
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183674:5"/>buy Chriſtians for their ſlaves; which being taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, and <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror proving their enemy; the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> are ſtirred up by him to their converſion or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation.<note place="margin">Ammonis <hi>l. b 4. Hiſt.</hi> Hiſp.</note> Under <hi>Theodebert</hi> and <hi>Theodorick</hi> Kings of <hi>France</hi> they enjoyed the moſt ſerene times; but <hi>Dago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> joyns with <hi>Seſebodus</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> to their undoing: Yea ſo odious afterwards became they to Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Pertrus Cluni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acenſis.</note> that ſome perſwading Chriſtian Princes to the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Holy Land out of the hands of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Saracens; their goods are preſently pointed at, as moſt fit to pay the Souldiers wages: yea ſome flew ſo high to pronounce the only way,<note place="margin">Rodulphus vilis. Papirius Meſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>in Lud. 7.</hi>
               </note> to obtain their ancient Countrey from the Infidels, was to take away their lives here; as fighting more againſt the Cauſe by their ſuperſtition and cruelties (which being ſuffered made God diſpleaſed) then the other by their ſwords and military Engines.</p>
            <p>A ſtop was given to this heady and raſh ſentence by the interpoſition of St. <hi>Bernard</hi> and others. But as if ſuch miſchief nothing concerned them, ſome of them ſeated about <hi>Orleance,</hi> in the year one thouſand, ſent an Ambaſſage to the Prince of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Papirius Meſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ex Glabo.</hi>
               </note> ſtirring him up againſt the Chriſtians. The Ambaſſador ſuſpected and examined, the truth is diſcovered; they are thence run upon, and deſtroyed as Monſters of men, by the People.</p>
            <p>Not long after they arrive here in this Iſland;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stow, Holinſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Baker, ſay they were firſt of al admitted by him; if there were any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here in the Land, they were but very few.</note> about the year 1070 firſt of all admitted by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, being brought from <hi>Roan</hi> by him. Their good welcom in other parts was no cauſe of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee this Country. He had made room enough for them, by that hav<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had made of the Engliſh
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183674:6"/>Nation: little good will bare he to it; and this was never taken by it as a ſign of his contrary diſpoſition. He and all his Succeſſors intended to uſe them to their own advantage, dealing with them as ſpunges; ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſuck up the Engliſh treaſure, which they then ſqueeze out into their own Coffers. For in his fourth yeer, holding a Council of his Barons, he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons up 12. out of each County;<note place="margin">Roger de Hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>in</hi> Hen <hi>2.</hi> Wilielmus rex. <hi>4.</hi> anno regni ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> commands them to ſhew their Laws and Cuſtoms, and agree upon that, which afterwards was held authentick. Here it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that the Jews ſetled in the Kingdom (as the title runs) ſhould be under the Kings protection; that they ſhould not ſubject themſelves to any other without his leave: it is declared that they and all theirs are the Kings; and if any ſhould detain any of their goods, he might challenge it as his own.</p>
            <p>Being here thus brought in and ſettled, they loſe no time: by their great extortion they fill their purſes for the treaſury, and the Engliſh treaſure up prejudice and heart-burnings againſt them; both which will be ſhewed in the ſequel of our ſtory; when, mixing the blood of innocents with their ſacrifices, they made ſo great impreſſion on the Engliſhmens hearts, as ſcarce ever will be worn out with the ſtrength of time; and then never could be ſatisfied but with their expulſion.</p>
            <p>Indeed, in the days of K. <hi>William</hi> the ſecond, little of tranſaction occurs in reference to them, but what was cauſed by his own means. That Kings Scepticiſm in Religion,<note place="margin">Baker. Will. Malmsbu. <hi>in</hi> Will. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> or rather profaneneſs, did but increaſe the fury of their Superſtition. Being at <hi>Roan</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> he takes upon him, for a reward, to reduce one who was turned Chriſtian to his former ways again; but being not able to perform his promiſe, and put to a ſtand by his young adverſary, he bids him be gone
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183674:6"/>out of his preſence, but keeps half of the money to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And here at <hi>London</hi> he makes a diſputation be held betwixt the Chriſtians and them. The Biſhops aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the King is preſent, &amp; promiſes to paſs into the Jews cauſe, if clearly conquerors. They are ſaid to have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away nothing but confuſion; but this came of it, that afterwards they became more confident; ſtiffly affirming themſelves not to have been overpowerd with reaſon, but faction.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſolency of their carriage in this buſineſs wrought grudges in Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Will. Ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> which, joyned with the natural enmity to them as Jews, might have done more, if the joy conceived for the Kings ſtability, and their own victory, had not ſomething allayed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and as yet ſcarce knowing one another: there wanted experience of the Jews conditions, which time produced; when growing ſecure through peace and plenty, they eaſily betrayed themſelves.</p>
            <p>Throughout the reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, we hear nothing of them. As yet they were not ſo fully ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; coming over, removing from place to place, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding themſelves ways of livelyhood; and were ſo active, as though they were not many at the firſt, and ſcarce for a while reſiding any where but at <hi>London;</hi> yet ſhortly they wre ſpread throughout the whole Land; no Town at all conſiderable, but multitudes in it.</p>
            <p>At the firſt they had this advantage, that through the Engliſh peoples ignorance of their manners (for the generality) and the horridneſs of them (which afterwards appeared) they might have opportunity to conceal their malice againſt the truth. Yet at length it is fully diſcovered; when in the year 1144. and the ninth of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> all Laws of humanity broken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monum.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:183674:7"/>all ingenuity which ought to be ſhewed by ſtrangers towards them that harbor them; in a malitious oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt the truth, and furious deſpight againſt Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the world: in the City of <hi>Norwich</hi> they lay violent hands upon a poor infant; which, following the example of their Anceſtors, they moſt cruelly cruefie and murder.</p>
            <p>What the Chriſtians might think hereupon, we may eaſily judge; what indignation and implacable hatred might ariſe: and that not only in reſpect to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; but out of ſollicitation for the children of their own bowels, who, living amongſt them, might eaſily be inſnared, catched, and miſerably butchered: when any childe was miſſing, ſuſpitions and jealouſies could not but abound.</p>
            <p>This they could not be ignorant of, and how by this means they digged pits to fall into themſelves.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monum.</note> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, having got a taſte of Chriſtian blood, and delighting much in that wretched cruelty, ſeventeen years after, and the ſeventh of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, in the Town of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> they act the former part over again,<note place="margin">Stow in his Survey of <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> crucifying another child in like manner, in ſcorn and deriſion of our Saviour and Profeſſion. This together with clipping and ſpoiling the coyn, might juſtly have provoked more then we can read of. No great ſtir was made about it, though ſuch acts were not likely long to be tolerated with more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry patience. Yet this King, inſtead of taking ſuch courſe with them as they might deſerve, rather ſtrives, and bears with ſuch enormities; takes away no privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but adds unto them. For whereas ever before, for the ſpace of 100. years, they had had no burying place allowed them any where but at <hi>London;</hi> and ſo were conſtrained to bring all their dead from the moſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183674:7"/>remote parts hither:<note place="margin">Rog. de Hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>in</hi> Hen. <hi>2.</hi> Stows <hi>ſurvey.</hi> Hollinſh.</note> he gives them leave upon their Petition at the Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> to purchaſe ground convenient for their ſervice in all places; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it were without the Town walls.</p>
            <p>In the year 1189. King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond dieth;<note place="margin">Hollinſh. Speed.</note> and before this his ſon whom moſt unfortunately, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, he had aſſumed to the Government, and made partaker of his Kingdom: ſome think this young King to have born no great good will to the Jews, and that he would have manifeſted the ſame, had he ſurvived his father. But he dying, <hi>Richard</hi> ſucceeds, of that name the firſt. Now the people begun to be very weary of theſe their gueſts: beſides what's ſaid, being grievouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with their uſury. Now alſo were they reported to do miſchief in companies where they came, &amp; poyſon men and women, as they had done the wels in <hi>Germany</hi> during the troubles betwixt the Emperour and Pope. Whereupon King <hi>Richard</hi> the day before his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Krantius Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal. <hi>Hiſt. lib. 9.</hi>
               </note> forbids any of them by Proclamation, or their wives to come within the Church or Palace, during the ſolemnity. They as yet having not experienced the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the people, or expecting impunity for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, they intended to offer approach neer the Court gate:<note place="margin">Chron. Weſt.</note> whereof the Chieftain with divers of his affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity enter. Hereupon a Chriſtian ſtrikes one of them with his hand, bidding him ſtand further off, as the King had commanded; whereat others taking occaſion, as watching for an opportunity, lay at them with ſtones and other things that come to hand; whereof enſues the death of ſome, and hurt of many.</p>
            <p>It happened, that one of them being hurt in the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult,<note place="margin">Matth: Paris <hi>in</hi> Rich. <hi>1.</hi> Holinſh.</note> deſired to be baptized, which he was accordingly; but being brought before the King and examined, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced again the Chriſtian Faith:<note place="margin">Polydor. Virg.</note> whereupon the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183674:8"/>King looking upon the Biſhops, and demanding what was to be done with him; the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> wiſely replied; If he will not be a childe of God, then let him be a childe of the devil; but others would have had him dealt with after another faſhion.</p>
            <p>But the noiſe of what was done at Court preſently arrives in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. Paris, Speed, Holinſh.</note> Then the heady multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, having got what they wiſhed, preſently make to the <hi>Jews</hi> houſes; but finding them entred, and the doors locked, ſome they break open, pillage and rifle the houſes; thoſe that are too ſtrong they ſet on fire, the owners miſerably periſhing in the flames; and thoſe that come forth are unmercifully received on the points of ſwords and ſpears, by their implacable and furious enemies. Tidings hereof being brought to the King, he diſpatches away <hi>Rich. de Glanvill</hi> his chief Juſtice, and other Miniſters of State, to appeaſe the People; but they being little reverenced, and their authority as little regarded, return again as they came, having only ventured their lives to no purpoſe. This laſted from the noon of one day, to two a clock of the next and then the rout broke up: inquiſition was made for offenders, and ſome executed; ſome houſes of Chriſtians having alſo periſhed, and much harm done.</p>
            <p>This on the morrow draws out a proclamation from the King,<note place="margin">Matth. Paris, Holinſh.</note> to the end the like for the future might be prevented; none under great penalties are to hurt or moleſt a Jew. But the King having taken upon him the Croſs, and having croſſed the Seas into <hi>France;</hi> upon his expedition into the Holy Land, the people take occaſion at his abſence, having the memory of the ſtirs at <hi>London</hi> freſh in their minds, to ſatisfie their greedy deſires in the Jews deſtruction, in divers parts of the Realm.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:183674:8"/>
            <p>Yet the occaſion was given by themſelves:<note place="margin">Polidor. Virgil. Holinſh.</note> That free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from moleſtation which was indulged to them by the King, they will not beſtow upon one of their own Nation. It hapned in <hi>Lin,</hi> that one of them turned Chriſtian, and being for that mortally hated by them, they ſought occaſion to take away his life, reſolving to kill him where ere they meet him. Accordingly meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him on a time in the ſtreets, they ſell upon him. He to ſave his life, betakes himſelf to the next Church; whither they alſo purſuing him, break it open. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a tumult is raiſed by the crying out of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians who earneſtly endeavoured to ſave the Convert; and with that, many of the Inhabitants, and divers Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nors (who were ſtrangers) came in unto the reſcue. The Jews are beaten home to their houſes; which the Sailers out of greedineſs of gain, rob, rifle, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage; and ſetting them on fire, get them to their ſhips, hoiſe up ſails, and away they go. Thus God raiſes up even ſtrangers (who came thither to trade) to ſcourge this crooked and rebellious people.</p>
            <p>The next place which took the alarum was S. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundſbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> on the 15 of <hi>March,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holinſh.</note> and the 2 of the King; when they being no leſs hated for their cruel oppreſſion, are ſet upon by the people, plundred and ſlain. Things were ſooner compoſed here by the care of the Abbot, and the reſidue of the Jews expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Town, never to return thither again. At <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and at <hi>Lin</hi> alſo at the ſame time, were great ſtirs, all places deſiring nothing more, then to be rid of theſe their gueſts.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt commotion was at <hi>York;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Paris. alii.</note> when the hand of God ſeverely puniſhed their ſtubbornneſs and cruelty: There, <hi>March</hi> the 17. in the ſame year, the people envying the happineſs of thoſe Towns who ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183674:9"/>uſed them, ſet moſt violently upon them, forcing them for ſafety to take their heels. Hence four or five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fly to Towers to ſave themſelves; where being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, and ſeeing little hopes to eſcape the danger, one of their Rabbies makes an Oration to them, exhorting them rather to kill one another, then fall into their hands who oppoſed their Law: He begins firſt, cuts his wives throat (whoſe name was <hi>Anna</hi>) next his childrens, then his friends, and laſtly his own; the reſt follow his example, throwing their ſlain relations over upon their Chriſtians heads. Some in another Tower, hearing what was become of theſe, ſet the place and themſelves on fire, calling upon their companions hard by to do the like; but theſe eſteeming better of their lives then ſo, offer to yield, on condition, that for turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians, and being baptized, they might have them ſpared.</p>
            <p>This is agreed upon and concluded, but they coming out, were moſt perfidiouſly &amp; cruelly butchered, malice and paſſion breaking the bounds of faith given. After this maſſacre, the people run to the Cathedral, get all their Bonds and Obligations into their hands, by which they had bound many a man unto them ſo unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, as if the Authors were not of credit which report it, it were incredible. But all theſe, a fire being made in the midſt of the Church, they reduce to aſhes.</p>
            <p>Now the King was beyond the Seas, on his way to <hi>Paleſtine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Paris &amp; alii.</note> but receiving this news, hears it with great indignation, fretting that his orders being ſo little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, his authority ſhould be ſo much infringed; as alſo, for that he had received upon his ſetting forwards, great ſums of money from the Jews; wherefore he ſends his commands to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> to ſee theſe inſurrections ſeverely puniſhed. The Biſhop, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183674:9"/>to theſe injunctions, marches down to <hi>York</hi> with a great Army, but miſt his prey, the chief Actors in the Tragedy being fled into <hi>Scotland</hi> upon the rumor of his coming. The Magiſtrates and chief Citizens excuſed themſelves, as not acceſſary to the fact, which was committed principally by the Souldiers (who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing croſſed and gathered together, were to paſs over to the King, and follow him on his expedition) and other Countrey people, which flocked thither from the Towns near adjoyning. But the ſtout Biſhop would not be ſatisfied with this put off, but fleeced the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, the multitude being pardoned, for that the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of the rout were fled away. The Inhabitants of <hi>Lin</hi> excuſed themſelves, laying the matter upon the Sailers, and had little ſaid unto them.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth year of this Kings reign, 1194. <note place="margin">Rog Hoved. in Rich. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> were Juſtices Itinerant ſent throughout the Land in <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Amongſt other Inſtructions, this is given them in charge, to enquire diligently of murthers of Jews; of the Jews Pledges, Goods, Lands and Writings: Commiſſioners and places are appointed to inroll all their Debts, Pledges, Lands, Rents, and Poſſeſſions, and great penal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies appointed to the breakers of theſe orders, according to that above-mentioned, that they and all theirs are the Kings.</p>
            <p>All this while theſe ſeveral Kings bore with them, by reaſon of the profit which redounded to their coffers; yet no great damage did they hitherto ſuffer. But now their actions rendring them more and more obnoxious, as well as their Religion; and having hoarded up abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of wealth, to the undoing of the ſubject, from henceforth they become a prey to the Prince, as often as his neceſſities call upon him; who knowing where to have ſupply, forces them always by ſtrong hand to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183674:10"/>diſgorge themſelves; which provoking them for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit to double their diligence, the people come to pay for it at the laſt.</p>
            <p>Now had King <hi>John</hi> ſucceeded his brother,<note place="margin">Matth. Weſtin.</note> a Prince ſufficiently covetous and griping. Being in want, or at leaſt pretending it; in his eleventh year 1210 he commands all the Jews of both Sexes, throughout his Kingdom, to be apprehended; impriſons them, and inflicts great puniſhments upon them, that they might empty themſelves to fill his purſe; ſome he commands to have an eye pull'd out: one at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> being more reſolute then his fellows, ſtands it out, refuſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem his liberty at ſo great a rate as the King required.<note place="margin">Matth. Paris.</note> He to take a ſpeedy and certain way with him as he thought, commanded he ſhould every day, as long as he refuſed to ſubmit,<note place="margin">K. <hi>John</hi> in the firſt of his raign, granted them ſuch a priviledge as can ſcarce be paralleld, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king one <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> of <hi>London</hi> High-Prieſt, that ſo they might acrifice, which elſe could not be done. <hi>J. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cok.</hi>
               </note> have a tooth pull'd out of his head. The poor man had but eight in all; ſtood out ſeven days; then, having but one tooth left him, to ſave that, agrees to the Kings demand, and pays the money.</p>
            <p>By this time their iniquities were grown ſo high, that they were counted a burden to the earth on which they trod; no riſing, no ſtir, but part of it muſt fall upon them. In the Wars betwixt the King and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, the City of <hi>London</hi> was taken by the Barons men; who, preſently breaking in, fall upon the Jews, deſtroy them as the common plague,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stows</hi> ſurvey.</note> and raſe their houſes down to the ground; of the ſtones of which <hi>Ludgate</hi> was afterwards partly repaired; as appeared by an inſcription in a ſtone, when the gate was builded the laſt time.</p>
            <p>King <hi>John</hi> after this leaves this life,<note place="margin">Speed.</note> and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alſo to a childe in a ſad condition Now was <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Dolphin</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and the royal prerogative in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183674:10"/>the hands of the Barons: yet by the honeſty and prudence of the Earl of <hi>Pembrook,</hi> all things were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a quiet ſtate condition; the aliens expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and peace ſetled. The Jews during his non-age were little moleſted; but in his 14. year 1230. they did ſufficiently ſmart. K. <hi>H</hi> 3. is for <hi>France,</hi> and wanting money, whither ſhould he betake himſelf, but to their purſes; he gets the third part of all their movables,<note place="margin">Hollinſh.</note> and away he goes.</p>
            <p>What people in the world would not have laid theſe things to heart, and ſtriven by the amendment of their lives to have hindred ſucceeding plagues? but wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is that people which commits iniquity by a Law, and whoſe very principles of Religion prompts them to horrid and unlawful actions. They count it no ſin, but rather the contrary, even to commit murder, ſo they can but thereby ſcoff at and deride the Chriſtian profeſſion. Some five years after the Kings going in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> keeping his <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Jews are brought before him by one <hi>Tolie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm.</note> and grievouſly accuſed. They had gotten a childe at <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> and had circumciſed him, calling him <hi>Jeremiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 16. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at. Paris</note> kept him a year together, intending to crucifie him at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> when they ſhould meet together for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The thing was confeſſed by them, and they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon caſt into priſon, abiding there the Kings pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Now begun this Prince to be ſore pinched with want. Coming to the Crown ſo extream young,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Rob. Cotton.</note> he wanted that experience which others might attain, who having not ſo much of their will at firſt, by diſcipline, with years might gather experience. His Minions coſt him dear; he flew to that height in laviſhments, that at laſt he was conſtrained to break up houſe, and betake himſelf to the Monks, to take his Commons.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183674:11"/>This could not but turn to the Jews coſt and diſquiet. He ſo orders the matter,<note place="margin">Baker.</note> that one <hi>Abraham,</hi> found to be a delinquent; redeems himſelf with 7000. marks: and <hi>Aaron</hi> proteſts the King hath ſince his laſt being in <hi>France</hi> taken from him, at times 30000. marks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides 200. of gold given to the Queen.</p>
            <p>In the year 1239. they are grievouſly fined again; paying the fifth part of all their movables. They had committed a murder ſecretly, and the King takes hence occaſion to empty their purſes; imploying <hi>Geofrey Templar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Paris</note> one of his Minions, in the Collection. About this time alſo they are reported to have done over that at <hi>Norwich</hi> again, which they did ſome 4. years before; circumciſing another childe, whom they called <hi>Jurnin,</hi> who is alſo deſtined by them to the Croſs. But the juſt God turned the miſchief upon their own heads, the childe being in time diſcovered, whileſt his father heard him crying in the Jews houſe. <hi>William de Raele</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, with other of the Nobility, being inraged for the fact, apprehend all that live in the Town. The Jews pretending the Kings protection, the Biſhop an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, It belongs not to the King, but to the Church, to Judge this matter of Circumciſion: wherefore four of them, being drawn at horſes tails to the place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,<note place="margin">Krantzius <hi>lib. 7.</hi> Wandal.</note> receive their reward. At <hi>Prague</hi> alſo they are ſaid this year to have crucified a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And that which ſhewed their faithfulneſs ſufficiently, and procured them ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red not in the leaſt degree,<note place="margin">Holinſh. Ex Eulog. <hi>and</hi> Fox <hi>Acts and Monum.</hi>
               </note> was, that in the year 1253. at <hi>Northampton</hi> they combined together, and that for the deſtruction of that City, which firſt harboured them; preparing to ſet even the City of <hi>London</hi> on fir<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. This could not but enrage much; yet having entred ſuch courſes as rendred them more then odious, they are reſolved to go on, though
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183674:11"/>to their own deſtruction. But what they intended to do to the City they ſuffer themſelves; for many of them being taken in the ſame Town where they hatcht their deſign, are themſelves reduced to aſhes, in the time of Lent.</p>
            <p>And this year alſo were they expelled out of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm.</note> by command of King <hi>Philip,</hi> who then warred in their ancient Countrey.<note place="margin">Matth. Paris.</note> The Saracens there expoſtulating with him for his violence offered to themſelves, who never injured Chriſt; upbraid him with the foſtering them in his realm, who were his murderers. The cauſe was religion, and he thought all things reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it were to be removed: to ſtop therefore the Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens mouths, this people muſt quit their habitations.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> was now about this time beyond the Seas,<note place="margin">Matth. Paris.</note> making a viſit to his French Dominions; and there wanting money, ſends over his brother <hi>Richard</hi> to procure it. The Nobility, for the moſt part, plainly deny to help him with any; but as for the Jews they are a ſure refuge, they are fleeced at all hands, and they might thank their purſes that here they lived. Not long after returning home; and having ſpent an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ſum of money in his journey, and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a great debt; (being put off by his Barons) he betakes himſelf again to his never failing treaſury: he ſqueezes the Jews again; and yet having preſſed out almoſt both blood and moiſture, turns them over unto his brother. He pittying their condition, little moleſts them; but upon pawns ſupplies the King with a great ſum of money.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay to a people that is given up to a reprobate minde? and commits iniquity with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs? whom neither fear of God, of the Laws, love unto mankinde, nor the dictates of humanity can
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183674:12"/>bridle and reſtrain? whoſe blindneſs is ſuch, whoſe ſtubborneſs is ſo great, that no experience can reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, no affliction can leſſen? They are not yet ſatisfied with Chriſtian blood, they will rather venture all, then not vent their malice againſt Chriſtian profeſſion. They have another annual Tragedy to act, and <hi>Lincoln</hi> for this year muſt be the Stage. There in that City in the year 1255. they get a child into their hands of eighteen years of age; whom after many cruel whippings, ſcourgings,<note place="margin">Matth. Paris, Holinſh. alii.</note> and tortures, they again crucifie and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: In deriſion of Chriſt a <hi>Pilate</hi> is made, before whom he is brought, accuſed and condemned; ſuffering their malice in the ſame manner as our Savior had done before, they imitating as near as they can their anceſtors in this their horrid and abominable act. Being dead the childe is thrown into a well, near the ho<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re this butchery was committed. The poor woman miſſing her ſon, and inquiring after him, finds he was ſeen playing laſt, before that door with the Jews children: and hence upon ſuſpition the well is ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the body found. The man of the houſe being apprehended and examined by <hi>John Lexinton,</hi> upon promiſe of pardon, confeſſes the murder, acknowledges it to be their cuſtom every year to crucifie a child, but very ſecretly, and therefore not eaſie to be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The King would not ſuffer the man to live, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently commands his execution, when coming to die, he accuſes moſt of the Jews in <hi>England</hi> as acceſſory to the Fact; it being their cuſtom (upon notice given) moſt of them to meet upon ſuch a wicked occaſion. In <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> an hundred &amp; two were carried up to the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> &amp; thence were commanded to the Tower; of theſe afterwards 18. were hanged, the reſt remain'd long time in priſon. The body of the child
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183674:12"/>(whoſe name was <hi>Hugh</hi>) was honorably buried in the Cathedral, and he ever after accounted a Martyr.</p>
            <p>About two years after, hapned a thing in <hi>Teuxbury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hollinſh. Mat. Paris.</note> which perhaps might as well be omitted as ſpoken of. It chanced there, that a Jew fell into a Jakes on <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> which being their Sabboth, he would not that day be drawn out for breaking of it. The Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> hearing this news, forbids him to be taken out the next, on Sunday; for that neither (he ſaid) ſhould the Chriſtian Sabboth be broken by him; whereupon the poor man lying there till Munday, miſerably died. Of this ſtory, I have read theſe verſes rimed, according to the Poetry of that age:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tende manus, Solomon, ut te de ſtercore tollam.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sabatta ſancta colo, de ſtercore ſurgere nolo:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sabatta noſtra quidem Solomon celebrabis ibidem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the year, 1262. and of this <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. the 47.<note place="margin">Holinſh. Stows <hi>ſurvey.</hi>
               </note> a Jew little remembring into what a tickle condition their deſerts had brought them, wounds a Chriſtian within <hi>Colechurch,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Cheap.</hi> He is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued home to his houſe by the multitude, and there ſlain; with whoſe life yet they would not be ſatisfied. But going on in their fury, they break up and pillage the houſes of that Nation, and kill divers, ſo full were the Londoners of prejudice and ſpight againſt them, that upon all occaſions they could not bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſcover it. But not onely againſt their perſons do they rage: The publike toleration of their Religion was alſo a great offence to them; running therefore to their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue at the weſt ſide of <hi>Olaves Jury</hi> (where they for the moſt part lived) they utterly deſtroy it. The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183674:13"/>ground being afterwards by the King given away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the ſeat of Friers, next of a Nobleman, then of a Merchant, and ſince that of the Windmil Tavern.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Reb Cottor.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But now ere long the ſparks of diſcontent and grudges betwixt the King &amp; Barons were quite blown up into a flame His laviſhments and neglect in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Juſtice, had ſubjected him to their plots and combinations, and betwixt both parties ſprung a more then civil War. The Barons had gotten the hearts of the Citizens; who eaſily drawn with the promiſes of freedom and reformation of abuſes, took their part; but the Jews (loving neither in reality) clave to the King, ſufficiently knowing their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in this matter, though at other times they could take no warning, but by their abominable actions, drew ſtill upon themſelves, one plague at the heels of another. But here they ſaw on whom they depended, what it was that kept them here, and what they might expect if the Barons ſhould prove victorious.<note place="margin">Holinſh. Ex Eulog.</note> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly therefore in the year 1264. they that inhabite in <hi>London</hi> reſolving to do what they may, plot the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Barons and Citizens altogether. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing except deſolation and miſery attending them, they are detected hereof, almoſt all ſlain, their houſes ranſack'd, abundance of treaſure being therein found ſcraped up together.</p>
            <p>But within a while providence had decided the civil quarrel,<note place="margin">Holinſh.</note> giving the victory unto the King: whereupon a Parliament was called, and many turned out of their eſtates being proſcribed by Law. Divers of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherited Gentlemen being thus out-lawed, and ſore repining at their condition, betake themſelves to the Iſle of <hi>Oxholm,</hi> whither reſorts a multitude of the baſer ſort, who rob and rifle the places near adjoyning,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183674:13"/>and act according to the cuſtom of men carried by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and deſperation. Now <hi>Lincoln</hi> being not far diſtant, is taken and ſacked by them; wherein not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindeful of the publique enemy, the Jews, they run to their Synagogue, which they burn, together with their Law; and many of them in it; thinking it even ſin if to their other robberies, they ſhould not add this of ſpoiling them, who in that place had broken the bounds of all humanity, and thereby deſerved many deaths.</p>
            <p>And now we come to the laſt paſſage we meet with, during the long raign of this King. Things ſeeming to be prettily ſettled, yet clouds begin to gather again. The Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> is unſatisfied with affairs, and the efore muſt up and make way for better fortune by his ſword. He comes up to <hi>London,</hi> and gets poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the City. The Jews then, their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, being ſenſible of the approaching of their ruine with the Popes Legat, flock into the tower, of which they have a part aſſigned them to defend. But things being after a while compoſed, they alſo for a while en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy quietneſs and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Now began the Engliſh liberty from theſe incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to draw on amain; for in the year 1272. King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt had aſcended the throne, ſucceeding his father. Their oppreſſions were now grown ſo in tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that longer they could not be endured, the people of <hi>England</hi> being almoſt ready to quit their dwellings, and leave them their habitations.<note n="*" place="margin">Math. Weſt, Edv. rex ad Parlamentum Weſtmonaſterii <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnes Nobiles regni ſui juſſerat congregari, in quo Statuta multa ad utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem regni fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt publicata, inter quae Judaeis fuit interdicta effraenatalicentia uſurandi: Et ut poſlent à Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis diſcerni, praecepit rex, quod inſtar ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bularum unius palmaelongitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſign a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in exterin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus indumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> Therefore in the third of the King a Parliament is called; and in it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, their unreaſonable uſury is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by Law; and for that they are accounted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any charitable thought, they are ordered to wear plates in their clothes, clear to be ſeen, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one might take notice who they were.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:183674:14"/>
            <p>But that they cannot get one way, they will have another; the meaſure of their iniquities was not yet compleat, and therefore they run on ſtill to their own deſtruction. Would any people under the cope of heaven, having had ſo many warnings, undergone ſo many troubles, ſuffered ſuch maſſacres, yet go on; as if to make amends, and procure themſelves ſafety, was to heap guilt upon guilt, and adde treachery to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence But in the year 1278. and the ſixth of the King, they waſh,<note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm. Paris.</note> clip, and counterfeit his coyn, as they had done before in the reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond. Being apprehended, they likewiſe accuſe the Chriſtians as acceſſary. At <hi>London</hi> nigh 300 are executed (amongſt whom there were three Chriſtians) many being alſo put to death in other places.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holinſhed.</note> according to the tenor of their hold here in <hi>England,</hi> and their obnoxiouſneſs to which their actions had reduced them, counted all they had his own; and for non-payment of what was demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the whole generation ſcattered through the whole Land, are ſhut up in one night, where they enjoyed no day, until they had fined at his pleaſure. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons now offered to the King the fifth part of their moveables to have them baniſhed;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but this Prince (having this opportunity his Predeceſſors wanted, of their vying with one another) makes his own markets, takes moſt that is offered; and ſo the Jews emptying their purſes, purchaſe their continuance a little longer. But vengeance preſſed them at their very heels, they acting ſuch an horrid murther this year beyond the ſeas, as is ſcarce to be thought, and (if not theirs) harder to be believed.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs the prejudice and antipathy betwixt the Engliſh Nation and them now was ſuch, as would not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183674:14"/>admit of any reconciliation, and thereupon might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers inconveniences proceed; but eſpecially the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement of their Religion, joyned with great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs of diſpoſition, plunged them into devilliſh and unheard of wickedneſs. This year they were generally impriſoned here in <hi>England,</hi> and (as we may ſay) as guilty (in approbation at leaſt) of what their Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men practiſed in other parts, who at <hi>Munchen</hi> in <hi>Bavere</hi> ſtabbed a childe throughout his whole body with needles,<note place="margin">Aventin. Boiorum annal. l. <hi>7.</hi> p <hi>442.</hi>
               </note> taking his blood in a baſon, to uſe it, as the ſuſpition was then, in ſacrifice, for ſtanching that iſſue of blood wherewith this people (Chriſtians know why) is continually peſtered. Theſe butchers were detected by the drover, an old Hag, taken in the very manner, while ſhe was ſtealing a ſecond for the ſame purpoſe. The bodie of the former being found out by her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, the freſh print of infinite wounds filled with gore, imploring vengeance, as it were with ſo many watered and blubbred eyes, ſo enrage the multitude, that they could not expect the Judges ſentence, but fall immediately upon theſe Jews, notwithſtanding the Princes ſervants, and their chief Magiſtrates earneſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to appeaſe the tumult, conveying as many Jews as they could into their Synagogue, which the people burning with fury, ſet on fire, and with it burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 180. Jews. But this by way of digreſſion, falling out in this year. Now to return again to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeveral Kings making their markets out of the Jews ſtore-houſes at all occaſions, the ſcore was to be diſcharged at the ſubjects coſt. Not content to let them rob the Countrey by their unmerciful dealings, they muſt alſo upon their wicked deſires, give them ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt juſtice it ſelf, for a little gain. It hapned, that in the 15. year of this King, 1288. he being then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183674:15"/>in <hi>Gaſcoin,</hi> a certain Knight ſued a Jew for the unjuſt detaining of a mortgaged Manor. The Jew ſhifts off the buſineſs, and for his diſcharge produces a protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on King <hi>Henry</hi> had granted him, that he ſhould never be convented before any Magiſtrate but himſelf alone.<note place="margin">Thom V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing.</note> Upon this the Knight goes over to the King, deſiring juſtice againſt his adverſary avoiding the equity of Law, by ſuch an unreaſonable priviledge. The King anſwers, it would not ſtand with reverence due to the memory of his Father, to make void that he had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this matter; but he would indulge him alſo this priviledge, that ſo he might be even with his adverſary, that what injury he or any other Chriſtian ſhould offer to that man, they ſhould not be bound to appear before any but himſelf alone, as long as the Jew ſhould ſtand upon his Charter. The Knight returns home with this anſwer; and his honeſt adverſary being acquainted with his ſucceſs, was glad to come to what accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Law would offer, no longer inſiſting upon his former grant.</p>
            <p>This peoples honeſty in this particular is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous. This man hath an intention to be wicked, and muſt have a priviledge for it. But counting of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans worſe then of Turks and Infidels, becauſe more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſing them in their way of ſuperſtition, what they might get any way, they counted it their own, and honeſtly enough; fear of puniſhment, no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bridling their malice.</p>
            <p>But ſuch like throws of their diſhoneſty, were but ſtill ſigns of their enſuing death, and of that delivery the Land was about to make of them; it being radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the nature of things, to unite their ſpirits, and double their diligence, againſt that which is ſhortly like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to work their ruine. Their iniquity being now fully
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183674:15"/>ripe, their time is alſo already accompliſhed. King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> is returned out of <hi>Gaſcoign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thom Wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſing. in. Edv. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and being honorably received of the Cle<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gie and Nobilitie, holds a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> ſuch as was likely to bring nothing but calamity to the Jews, for whoſe expulſion ſo much had been before this time offered. The people in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment are ſaid to be reſolved, rather to undo them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves once, then be always undoing their Religion, ſafety of their Children, and the Kingdom, honor and profit (which by the imbaſing and clipping of its coyn had gone to wrack) call upon them; and a fifteenth is offered to the King to have them expelled.<note place="margin">Vide Holinſh. in Edw. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> It ſeems they did not now overbid, for the fifteenth was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceped and an Act made, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 31, 1290. and the 18 of the King,<note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm.</note> that upon pain of hanging, they, their w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves and children, ſhould before the Feaſt of <hi>All-Saints</hi> next enſuing, depart the Land. Some ſay,<note place="margin">Wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſingham. Holinſh. &amp; alii.</note> they had onely money given them to bear their charges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into <hi>France.</hi> Others ſay, that all goods not move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, with their Tallies and Obligations, being confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, all other moveables, as gold and ſilver, they were licenſed to carry over. The number of them when they departed, was about 16511. many more then at their firſt coming; an increaſing miſery to the Land where ere they come.</p>
            <p>By vertue of this injunction,<note place="margin">Holinſh.</note> and in obedience to it they prepare for their removal. Divers of the richeſt hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a great ſhip, and therein having put much treaſure, are carried down the <hi>Thames</hi> towards the mouth of the River, beyond <hi>Quinborough;</hi> where the Maſter wickedly conſpiring with the Mariners to rob them of their riches, they are adviſed to go down out of the ſhip with him, and walk upon the ſands, to take the air. Having ſo done, and it being now flowing water,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183674:16"/>and the fands beginning to be covered, the Maſter is drawn up by a cord on ſhip-board; but they are then left expoſed, to be ſwallowed up of the waves: Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out for help, they are inhumanely bid to call upon <hi>Moſes</hi> for deliverance, and periſh miſerably by the floods. This greedineſs of gain in the Maſter and Mariners, was juſtly rewarded, he with others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arraigned and condemned by the Juſtices Itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and accordingly executed for ſo vile a fact, though little pity was had (for the generality) of them that periſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Ed Cook</note> being looked upon onely as purſued by the hand of divine juſtice.</p>
            <p>Now gone they are, and the Engliſh peoples diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet with them; and never ſince could they procure licence to return. King <hi>Henry</hi> the third founded an houſe for thoſe of them that ſhould be converted, in his 17 year;<note place="margin">Cambden. Stows Survey.</note> which afterwards in the 50 of <hi>Edward</hi> the third was again diſſolved, and appointed to the keeping of the Rolls, in which ſervice it continues to this day. King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt alſo cleanſing his Territories of the Jews,<note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm.</note> as ſo many locuſts, had before commanded, whilſt beyond the ſeas, that the parts of <hi>Aquitain</hi> ſhould likewiſe be ſwept of them.</p>
            <p>Thus I have proceeded as an Hiſtorian, keeping cloſe to that way, according as I am informed by our Writers. And hereupon I am not ignorant that ſome there are, and that not without reaſon, who may deny their aſſent to what is ſaid concerning their expulſion; being induced to believe the contrary, by greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then this report: The Oracle of Law in his time, pronouncing no Statute to have been made for their baniſhment. Judge <hi>Cook</hi> in the ſecond part of his Inſtitutes upon the Statute <hi>De Judaiſmo,</hi> affirms there was none, but onely that which was for the taking
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183674:16"/>avvay their Uſury, upon vvhich they left the Land, as he conceives, being ſo deprived of their Trade, or way of life. I have not arrived at that height of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, as to oppoſe ſo great a man, eſpecially in his own way; but yet ſhall tender ſomething to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I am warranted by Hiſtory, whereby I hope I ſhall eſcape the hazard of being thought to break the bounds of modeſty, being found onely in that way, in which at firſt I ſet forward. Our Hiſtorians all with joynt conſent, affirm them to have been actually baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or expelled; many of whoſe words I ſhall firſt ſet down, and then ſee onely what they might ſeem fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hint unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Bale<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m deſcript. Aug.</note> and approved<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſti <hi>31.</hi> Judaeorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperans multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tud<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quae per di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſas urbes &amp; caſtra fortia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitabat per re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troacta tempora confidenter juſſa eſt cum uxoribus &amp; parvulis ſuis unà cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonis ſuis mobilibus ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere circa feſtum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnium Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quod eis pro termino po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebatur, quem ſub poena ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dii transgredi non eſt auſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum numerus erat ut credeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>16511.</hi> Exierat antea tale edictum à laud<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bili rege Anglorum in partibus Aquitaniae, à quà omnes judaei pariter exulabant.</note> Author in his <hi>Flores Hiſtoriarum,</hi> at the 1290. year of our Lord, hath theſe words, <hi>Aug.</hi> 31. <hi>Judaeo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um exaſperans multitudo, &amp;c.</hi> On the third day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the exaſperating mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Jews, which in times paſt had lived confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in divers Cities and ſtrong Towns, is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their wives, children and moveables to depart <hi>England,</hi> about the Feaſt of <hi>All-Saints,</hi> which is ſet as the utmoſt limit of their continuance, which under pain of hanging they durſt not paſs, the number of whom was thought to be 16511. Such a Decree had gone out before from the commendable King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the parts of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> out of which in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Jevvs vvere baniſhed. So he. <hi>Thomas Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham,</hi> in his <hi>Hypodigma Neuſtriae,</hi> writes thus, <hi>Rex Angliaereverſus de Waſconia, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Rex Angliae reverſus de Waſconia Londoniis ſolemniter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eipitur à clero &amp; omni plebe. Qui Judaeos omnes eodem ann<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expellens de Anglia, datis expenſis in Gallias, bona corum reliqua confiſcavit.</note> The King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being returned out of <hi>Gaſcoign,</hi> is ſolemnly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Clergy and all the people at <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:183674:17"/>who the ſame year expelling all the Jews out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> giving them to bear their charges over into <hi>France,</hi> confiſcated the reſt of their goods; and <hi>Polydor. Virgil,</hi> in his ſeventeenth Book, at the 1290. year of Chriſt, delivers the matter thus: <hi>Anno deinde qui, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> deinde qui inſecutus eſt, Concilium L<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni ad <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterium ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur in qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis agita<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a eſt Ju<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um ejectio, quo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um erat per omnem Angliam ingers multitudo, qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> oves ab i oe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is ſegregarentur. Itaque publico edicto juſſum eſt, ut intra <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cos dies om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abirent cum bonis illi juſsis concilii parent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ili<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt.</note> Then in the year which followed, a Council was held at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in which firſt of all is debated the ejection of the Jews, of which there was through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi> a great multitude that ſo the ſheep might be ſeparated from the goats. Therefore it is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a publique Edict that within a few days all ſhould depart with their goods; they obeying the command of the Council went divers ways, thus far <hi>Polydor,</hi> who uſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the word <hi>Concilium</hi> for that we call Parliament; it with other words being (as a great<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> R. Cotton.</note> Antiquary ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves an uſual term in ancient Authors for that thing. <hi>Polych<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onicon.</hi> lib. 7. cap. 38. ſaith, the Jews were put out of <hi>England,</hi> and never came again. <hi>Stow</hi> in his Annals writes, that this year all the Jews were baniſhed this Land; for which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons gave a fifteenth. In like manner writes <hi>Holinſhead</hi> expreſly, that they were baniſhed by act of Parliament, and that a Fifteenth was granted to the King to have them expelled, that all their goods not moveable were confiſcate, with their Tallies and Obligations; all their other moveables of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the King licenſed them to convey with them; that they could never ſince obtain a priviledge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; and with theſe concurreth <hi>Speed,</hi> who tels us that the King to purge <hi>England</hi> (whither he was now returned) from ſuch corruptions and oppreſſions, as under which it gro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned, and not neglecting therein his particular gain, baniſhed the Jews out of the realm, confiſcating all their goods, leaving them nothing but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:183674:17"/>money to bear their charges.<note n="*" place="margin">Florilegus Dunſtable.</note> Others might be brought who teſtifie the ſame thing; neither is there any Hiſtorian, that I know, who denies it.</p>
            <p>Now ſtrange it is, that all theſe ſhould be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted and miſtaken, that thoſe of the near adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times to their departure ſhould ſo groſly erre, and that thoſe who lived in the ſame time, ſhould deliver to poſterity ſo great a falſhood. For if any had report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their departure to have been voluntary, it might have been found out by ſome of thoſe who ſucceeded and had their gatherings from them. <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſets down the day the Act ſhould be made for their expulſion, mentions the time ſet as the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt bound of their continuance, and withall the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty or puniſhment they were to ſuffer (even hanging) if found hereafter; and that the King had made ſuch adecree before for baniſhing them the parts of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine;</hi> a ſtrange thing that he ſhould ſo groſly erre in ſo many circumſtances. <hi>Walſingham</hi> writes that the King returned home, that he was met by the Clergy and all the people, and that this year they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled. <hi>Polydor</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Illi juſsis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii parentes, alii aliò diſceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> ſaith it was by Parliament, by its publike Edict, and that they obeying its commands departed; hinting unto us the end, that ſo the ſheep might be ſeparated from the Goats. <hi>Polychyronicon</hi> ſaith they were put out of, <hi>Stow</hi> that they were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of <hi>England; Holinſhead</hi> and <hi>Speed</hi> uſe the ſame term, this laſt adding alſo the Kings deſign, which was to purge the Land from ſuch corruptions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as under which it groaned; and alſo to fill his own Coffers; which was done pretty well, partly by the confiſcating of their goods, which all or moſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as alſo by the Fifteenth granted him by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to purchaſe their baniſhment, which ſome aver.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:183674:18"/>
            <p>We read, that about the year 1286. the Commons before offered the King the fifth part of their move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables to expel them, and it cannot but be likely they would alſo deſire the ſame at this Parliament; for though uſury was the main thing under which they groaned, yet there were other things they could not but be ſenſible enough of: <hi>viz.</hi> Crucifying of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and their great ſpight to Chriſtian profeſſion, with their late ſpoiling of the coyn. And ſcarce could this other Act againſt their uſury only give them hopes ſufficient that thence they would be driven away; for as we ſee before in the third of the King, their uſury was reſtrained and bounded, and other ways of life they might take up, and rather ſtay here with what they had already got, then by departing to loſe all, as it ſeems they did, though Judge <hi>Cook</hi> tels us, that there was proviſion made that no ſubject ſhould hurt or moleſt them; acknowledging alſo that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned fifteenth was given,<note place="margin">Pro expulſione Judaeorum.</note> and that too for their expulſion.</p>
            <p>This reverend Lawyer tels us this act <hi>de Judaiſmo</hi> was made in the 18. year of the King, but a little after the Feaſt of <hi>Hilary,</hi> whence theſe (perhaps imper<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inent) thoughts have ſometimes come in upon me; that if there was no miſtake of this year for the third of this King, in which formerly we read their uſury was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, then perhaps this ſame act <hi>de Judaiſmo,</hi> and the other for their baniſhment might be enacted in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Seſſions of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> this laſt, the 31. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> after, as <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> mentions, and the record loſt, the act being omitted in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Lawyers, as deemed of no uſe. And for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the record I am eaſilyer induced to think it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, becauſe I am credibly informed that that of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183674:18"/>act for eſtabliſhing the uſe of the Common-prayer Book was alſo miſſing heretofore, and thereupon ſome non-conformiſts eſcaped that which elſe had light upon them. And this I deſire to tender as an excuſe for my keeping cloſe to Hiſtory in which has lyen the work of this relation, nothing deſirous to impoſe upon the belief of any, or hereby to contradict ſo worthy an Author.</p>
            <p>Thus admitted by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, about the year 1070. they were expelled in the year 1290. being here ſome 220. years (longer by five or ſix then their Anceſtors were in <hi>Egypt</hi>) during which time we may eaſily ſee the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation was as in bondage. And by this Hiſtory impartially (though truly) related, may that Book ſufficiently be anſwered, by occaſion of which this was written; the profit which redound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them to this Nation, their ſaithfulneſs alſo being ſufficiently diſcovered upon which grounds the Rabbi raiſes his ſhort diſcourſe. But becauſe it may more clearly appear, and the Caſe may be more fully deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; we ſhall deſcend to his particulars, and ſcan them fully.</p>
            <p>The Author, though perhaps learned enough in other hiſtories, yet ſeems either utterly to be ignorant of ours, or elſe wittingly to decline that, which he knew would injure his cauſe ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>In his Epiſtle to his Highneſs the Lord Protector, he deſires that all Laws may be taken away, which ſtand in force againſt this innocent people made in times, and during the government of Kings. But if he pleaſe to turn his eye upon what hath been written; he may eaſily ſee, that it was not innocency, but the clear contrary that drew out theſe Laws againſt them; and for that he and his Country-men think this eaſier
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183674:19"/>to be procured ſince the Kingly Government is taken away; he may know that it was by the Kings alone they were kept here ſo long. The people would gladly have been rid of them, an hundred years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were; and deſired their expulſion above all things. Nay they offered a fifth part of their move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, to have them expelled; but King <hi>Edward</hi> only ſucking ſweet from them, and intending to make his Markets out of this contention, upon their offering more, gave them leave to buy their continuance for a little longer. And in the War betwixt <hi>Henry</hi> the third and his Barons, as is above declared, they ſtood for him, conſpired the ruine of them and the Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and that more for their own ends then out of any faithfulneſs to him.</p>
            <p>In his Declaration to the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> he acquaints us with the motives of his coming over: the firſt is to obtain free exerciſe of his Religion for his Countreymen. Here indeed it was anciently granted, but what good came of it? Its the deſire of this people to be fiſhing in troubled waters; they may have hopes in this juncture of time, to catch proſelytes; what his own deſign may be, I ſhall not queſtion; if we ſhould truſt him upon his word, it might be unſafe to deal ſo well with all his followers. Their Anceſtors compaſſed ſea &amp; land to make a proſelyte, and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes this to have been the cauſe of their expulſion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly out of <hi>Spain;</hi> but let us deſcend unto his ſecond.</p>
            <p>In this I cannot but wonder at the Rabbi. Its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that the time of their redemption is near (ſaith he) and that they muſt firſt be ſcattered throughout the world. What then? therefore if this be true, they muſt firſt have a Seat alſo in <hi>England.</hi> Why, they had a Seat here once before for the ſpace of above 200.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183674:19"/>years, and muſt they needs come again, or elſe their diſperſion (as to this place) cannot be accompliſhed?</p>
            <p>The third motive upon which he came over was for the benefit of our Nation, which he ſo much deſires, that which truly, if ſincere, we cannot but applaud, it being a thing not uſual for us to be ſo loved by that people. We cannot but thank him for his affection, but muſt a little queſtion his grounds by and by; when coming to his Book, we ſhall deſcend with him to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>His fourth motive is no leſs to be approved of: His particular reſpect to this Commonwealth is a motive to his ſollicitation for the readmiſſion of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. He might eaſilier, if he ſo much love us, have leave given him to continue; but we cannot but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he can ſcarce promiſe the like affection in all his brethren: and if he ſhould, its ſooner ſaid then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. And whereas he commends hoſpitality and kindeneſs to ſtrangers ſo much to our conſideration; our Nation was never unkind or churliſh; but the Jews too much familiarity with it heretofore, has put them out of the influence of hoſpitality.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the Book it ſelf. Three things he propoſes to his Highneſs the Lord Protector, as making a people well-beloved or deſirable amongſt all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>viz. Profit accruing from them, Faithfulneſsin them, and Nobility of Extraction;</hi> all which he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to the Jewiſh Nation. Profit indeed is the thing that all Kingdoms and States much look after, and with good reaſon; for money is the comfort of peace, and the ſinews of war; but ſuch profit is onely deſirable, as is joyned with glory to God, honor to the Magiſtrate and Countrey, and the ſafety and proſperity of the ſubject. Upon which grounds, if I ſhould grant him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183674:20"/>the application of profitableneſs to themſelves; yet ſhould I think it over-dear to be purchaſed with ſuch effects as might accompany it. God ought to be the beginning and the end; and Religion, the way of his Worſhip, is principally to be regarded. Now tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which is contrary to it, or a receiving of them which would endanger it, which would not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a ſuffering of Superſtition to be practiſed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oters, but be alſo an occaſion to the Natives of this miſcarriage, is ſcarce to be warranted; however there where as yet, it is not admitted. There be certain times and ſeaſons, which make that at one time dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, which might at another be admitted with more ſecurity. The truth is apt to have not onely fickleneſs &amp; weakneſs accompanying it, but alſo great differences and diſſentions, although incorruptible in it ſelf; and many though not agreeing in all things, yet may be contained within the verge of its neceſſaries and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals. Where the greateſt power of Religion is, there the Devil is the buſieſt; ſowing Tares amongſt the Wheat, and mixing the corn with his cockle. This we muſt confeſs is the condition of our Countrey at preſent; and I fear the Jews too well conſider it. By ſo much the more therefore as they may deſire to come in, doubtleſs in this reſpect the State hath as great to deny them.</p>
            <p>Honor and Credit is the ſecond thing by which a State ought to rule, and according to which, order and bound its profit. It was a ſaying of that renowned Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camb. in Eliz.</note> Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> when about his Charge in the Revenue, that nothing was fit for a Prince, that was not alſo joyned with honor; and that he did not like that the Treaſury ſhould fill like the Spleen, when the whole body was worſe for it. Now
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183674:20"/>what honor it would be to admit them, who were once<note n="*" place="margin">Judge <hi>Cook</hi> himſelf ſaith, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Act <hi>De Judaeaiſmo was</hi> made in<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them, and that the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was <hi>pro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne Judae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> expelled before; of whoſe worth, faithfulneſs and profitableneſs we have once experienced in our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, I cannot determine. But this ſecond rule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends eſpecially upon that which precedes, and of this which follows.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge, that whilſt they were here before, much profit redounded to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> from them: but in what way, hath been declared; not from their merchandizing, upon which our adverſary princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally inſiſts. Our countrey is not ſo convenient for that way as others may be; and if they ſhould be here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted again, &amp; ſpread once more throughout the land, thouſands there would be, which could not have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to exerciſe that way, through the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of their habitations. They exerciſe themſelves in that way of life which moſt ſuits with their profit, and the commodiouſneſs of the place wherein they live. Uſury was moſt practiſed by them here; and is ſtill in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other parts, where they have not ſuch opportunity of trading. But grant that the trade is now enlarged, through the diſcovery of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt Indies</hi> by ſea, and of <hi>America;</hi> as it is enlarged, ſo alſo more of our inhabitants follow that cou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe then formerly, being ſufficient to ſatisfie for that buſineſs: So that if the Jews be admitted to trade again, our Merchants muſt needs be juſtled by them; and what would redound to the State in Cuſtom and Exciſe (the Land being already ſufficiently furniſhed) would not compenſate the damage of the ſubject. If many ſhould be ſuffered to trade, this could not be avoided; and if not, then needs muſt they betake themſelves (their number encreaſing) to ſome other courſe of life, which might prove no leſs dangerous, they being
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183674:21"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Perfida gens, agens quod ſolet musin pera, &amp;c. Crantzius Saxon. lib. 11. cap. 7.</note> noted to be as ſucking Leaches where ere they come, in ſome way or other. But if they ſhould trade with other Countreys, rather in way of Sale and Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leſs profit would the State receive from them.</p>
            <p>He magnifies the skill his Countreymen have in all kinds of merchandize; and that is occaſioned, as he confeſſes, by the oppcrtunity they have (being every where diſperſed) to ſerve one another. And would not this turn to their own advantage, more then to the benefit of their entertainers? Might they not hereby ingroſs the Trade wholly to themſelves, and ſerving one another, cheat the Natives in their Traffick? And what would the Engliſh be better for their trafficking with their Countreymens money who live in <hi>Spain?</hi> for larger their banks vvould be, more they vvould engroſs the trading. And if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſavv it profitable for him, he vvould ſo far diſpenſe in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, as to give them no occaſion of removing from or keeping this treaſure out of his Dominions. And vvhat though they have not a Countrey to repair to, as other ſtrangers; and thereby (as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges) are not likely to take avvay their riches? Can they not tranſport it as they do (he tells us) in <hi>Spain?</hi> They ſhortly alſo expect (vve ſee) their Meſſias to come and reſtore them to the Countrey of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; and being aliens, they vvould little love the Countrey, and ſo do little for it, tending (by their good vvills) to any great advantage.</p>
            <p>If <hi>they be ſo well received, and live ſo happily all</hi> over (as he inſtanceth for illuſtration of this branch or <hi>profit</hi>) vvhy then are they not content to keep them vvhere they are already? It muſt needs be their ovvn good or ours, vvhich they ſo much deſire; or for that they muſt have a Synagogue here alſo, not vvilling
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183674:21"/>but that every place ſhould be bleſſed with their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. This he intimates expreſly, that they might have leave here alſo to ſerve God. Is it the ſoil or the air they deſire their Religion ſhould be ſeated in? why not as well ſerve God where they are? There's ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then this in the buſineſs.</p>
            <p>But by whom is it they are thus received and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? he confeſſes the people hate them generally, and muſt this be for nothing? In a fixed and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State, where factions do not bandy (ſuch as they are generally where they live) ſcarce is any grievouſly hated, but there is ſome notable cauſe for it. And if <hi>the King of</hi> Denmark <hi>hath invited them into his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi> or <hi>the Duke of Savoy, or of Modina;</hi> it is for ſome reſpect or other: Perhaps they may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for the ſame ends our Kings formerly ſo long retained them; <hi>viz.</hi> for their own gain, though much to the Subjects diſcommodity and trouble.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>they chiefly abound in the Turks Dominions,</hi> its no wonder. All the world knows the ſlavery of his Subjects; he counting all their goods his own, and they made for him (not himſelf for them) its no wonder if he care not how they be uſed, how pillaged, how op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. If <hi>he imploys the Jews ſo much in gathering his money,</hi> he knows them to be fit inſtruments for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He knows how to preſs and ſqueeze out of them what they have before ſucked up. All his Subjects leave him their heir at their death; no child having any of his fathers eſtate, but what he beſtows upon him. There they cannot but be eſpecially kept from riſings and inſurrections under that Government; which having ſo many Officers ſubordinate to one another, and the Countrey diſtributed to their charge, all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections (except great indeed) may be quickly daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183674:22"/>The Author goes not about to reckon up, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Baſſa's Beglerbegs, or Sanſacks there are of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: they are exempted, he ſaith, from going to war, and there's very good reaſon for it. For their Religion, the Turks account of them worſe then of Chriſtians: not ſuffering one of them to turn Turk, till he firſt be baptized. And when the Grand Signior dyes, what pillaging of them as well as Chriſtians, uſes there to be?</p>
            <p>After this, he reckons what numbers of <hi>Jews there are in Germany, Poland, Italy, Barbary, &amp; the Low-countreys, and how many are preferred to places of great Truſt and Influence;</hi> ſtill always acknowledging, how they are deſpiſed of the multitude. If they were profitable to theſe Countreys (the contrary whereof is ſeen for the moſt part by the grudges of the ſubject) he would ſcarce from thence neceſſarily make it follow, that their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction muſt alſo be convement for this Nation. If they have ſuch experience of them as this Land hath had, if gone, I believe they would ſcarce recal them. The Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> and King of <hi>Poland</hi> have tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated that, which put to the voyce of the people (for whoſe good they are, and ought to reign) would ſoon be removed; and in <hi>Poland,</hi> and thoſe places, ſo odious they are, that, as once here in <hi>England,</hi> they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in their habits, to be known from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, being noted alſo for that practice of Uſury, of which our adverſary would clear them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pope (with other Princes of Italy)</hi> ſucks not little profit from their oppreſſing of the people; he fares well by their extortion, and therefore willingly ſuffers them; eſpecially ſince the Reformation of Religion, out of emulation againſt the Proreſtants, whom he hates worſe then them or the Turks themſelves, as the Jew loves Turks above Chriſtians. The Republique
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183674:22"/>of <hi>Venice,</hi> and ſo that of the <hi>Low-Countreys</hi> tolerates them, and they may have particular reaſon for it. Their Government is ſuch, that thoſe who are Merchants, are alſo Senators, and few but they are found in both theſe ways, who are any thing conſiderable; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what they may hinder them in Trade, it is ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in cuſtoms, and other duties, equally redounding to the profit of all: whereas our Merchants being fewer in number, if the State ſhould be ſomething benefited by their Trade, and others thereby be ſomething eaſed, they alone would ſeel the weight of the burthen.</p>
            <p>But neither in the <hi>Low-Countreys</hi> are they ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly fond of their company; though ſcarce can they with conveniency (as things now ſtand) turn them oft, divers of their families being matched to them; cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs procuring that, which might be abhorred by Religion. So are they likewiſe in Portugal intermarti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the people being generally weary of their gueſts. Reaſon of State makes the Dutch-men tolerate all Religions but the Popiſh. From whence ſhall it not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be concluded, that all their neighbors ſhould do the like.</p>
            <p>And now I come to his ſecond thing which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes as a motive to receive them; and that is their <hi>Faithfalneſs and Honeſty.</hi> I think I might well ſpare my pams to anſwer this any further, then by what hath been already ſhewed. How faithful they have been to this <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et any impartial Reader Judge. <hi>They who ſhall out of ſcorn and hatred of our Profeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cruciſie children, lay violent hands on tender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants (and that by common practice) they who ſhall clip, counterfeit, and mangle our coyn, ſhall riſe up and butcher</hi> 200000 <hi>with unheard of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſend <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages to Pagans to ſtir them up againſt the common
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183674:23"/>name of Chriſtianity</hi> (wiſhing with <hi>Caligula,</hi> it had but one head) <hi>poyſon fountains, and the like;</hi> ſhall we count them faithful. They took part indeed with our <hi>Henry</hi> the third againſt his Barons; but it is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs to judge it done more for their own ends, then any faithfulneſs to the then Magiſtrate. If they have done ſometime that which is good in it ſelf; yet they have done it with ſuch malicious minds, that God hath given them but the reward of wickedneſs. So in the year, 1421. they furniſhed the poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with money and munition againſt their Antichriſtian Perſecutors,<note place="margin">Krantzius, l. <hi>11</hi> Saxon. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and therefore were quite baniſhed out of <hi>Bavere,</hi> quite bereft of all their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and coyn. And laſtly, baniſhed all the Dominions belonging to <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of that Province.</p>
            <p>Indignities offer'd to Religion in ſuch an horrid way, as by the <hi>vile butchery of poor innocents upon a croſs.</hi> can no way come in upon the account of <hi>faithfulneſs;</hi> and yet this they have ordinarily practiſed in other parts, as well before as ſince their expulſion. If they may finde an opportunity, what their will may be, we may gather from that their carriage, during the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles betwixt the Emperor and Pope; when hoping Chriſtian Religion would have dyed in thoſe wars &amp; ſeeing the ſtate of Chriſtendom deeply indangered in theſe civil broils,<note place="margin">Krantzius Wandal. Hiſt. l. <hi>9.</hi> cap <hi>23.</hi> Vide Baron. in Annal. ad ann. <hi>28. &amp; 1320. &amp; 13.48.</hi>
               </note> they according to their Jewiſh policy ſeek to thruſt it over head and ears in blood, poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fountains throughout <hi>Germany,</hi> offering like violence to the Sacraments, as they had uſed to do before.</p>
            <p>And we may further ſee their <hi>faithfulneſs and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> what it hath been ſince their expulſion, to go no further then to the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> In the year, 1568. and the ninth of her reign, they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:183674:23"/>by <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> the then Pope,<note place="margin">Hieron. Rub. lib. <hi>11.</hi> Hiſtor. Ravenna.</note> and that even for their <hi>horrid</hi> and <hi>extravagant Uſuries</hi> and <hi>Oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> for their <hi>combining with Thieves and Robbers;</hi> for <hi>Sorceries</hi> or <hi>Magical Charms,</hi> in <hi>winning women to their own and others luſts.</hi> And are we not ſatisfied with that <hi>horrid and abominable Treaſon of</hi> Lopez, by whom we have warning enough never to meddle with them more, as a people always working miſchief to this Nation? This Miſcreant taken in by the Queen to be her Houſhold Phyſitian, conſpires with her Spaniſh Enemies for money, to work her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and promiſes to poyſon her.<note place="margin">Cambden in Eliz.</note> Accordingly for that purpoſe he brings her a purge; but ſhe having by the ſpecial providence of God diſcovered his treachery (according to former agreement) ſends him with it to the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> telling him that he ſtood more in need of Phyſick. Upon this he carries it to the old man, deſirous at leaſt to diſpatch one of them: But he being too cunning for him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands what he hath there, and upon anſwer, a purge, telling him he muſt be a Phyſitian to purge ill humors out of him, preſently cauſeth him to be apprehended. Being convicted, and according to ſentence, brought to the place of execution, he there profeſſed that he loved Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as well as Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>The argument of their faithfulneſs, as to the Rabbi, is but very jejune; and therefore no wonder, if he produce ſo few examples. Firſt he mentions how faithful they were to the <hi>Kings of Egypt,</hi> and inſtanceth <hi>in the fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of</hi> Antipater <hi>to</hi> Julius Caeſar. For the firſt, they knew the power of the <hi>Ptolomies</hi> continually able to cruſh them; and therefore if ſome ſtood to them, and proved faithful, what did they herein but what their own advantage led them to, and what the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:183674:24"/>neceſſity of their State required. But how faithful were their Kings <hi>to the Babylonian Monarchs,</hi> to whom they did more then promiſe obedience? would they not always take their opportunity to rebel? And (becauſe he ſpeaks of their fidelity to the <hi>Romans</hi>) how came, I pray, the <hi>War with</hi> Veſpaſian, <hi>and</hi> Titus <hi>his Son?</hi> even, as before <hi>Zedekiah</hi> had rebelled againſt <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> and that proved the deſtruction of the City, ſo came it alſo to paſs the laſt time. It was an opinion ſtrong in thoſe days through the Eaſt, that <hi>Jewry ſhould bring forth the Monarch of the world:</hi> in confidence of this,<note place="margin">Vide Sueton in Veſpaſ.</note> the Jews rebel, ſlay the Governor, put to flight the Pro-Conſul of <hi>Syria; Veſpaſian</hi> is choſen General againſt them, there is choſen Emperor, and ſo the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Writers account that ſaying to be fulfilled; and then <hi>Titus</hi> is ſent into <hi>Judaea,</hi> and finiſheth the work begun by his father. How <hi>faithful they were in</hi> Adrians <hi>time,</hi> we ſhewed before in the Introduction; how they behaved themſelves alſo in <hi>Egypt, Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Rabbi inſtanceth ſome particular places and perſons; as the <hi>Jews of</hi> Bureos, <hi>who denyed obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to</hi> Don Pedro de Cruel, <hi>who had killed his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> how <hi>many Jews were made Tutors to Noblemens children;</hi> of <hi>Samuel Alvalenſi; the Jews carriage at the beſieging of</hi> Mantua, and in the <hi>Signory</hi> of <hi>Braſil.</hi> Theſe were but a few, if twenty times more, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the nature and carriage of the whole Nation, which how faithful it hath been, generally, to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all places, hath already been ſufficiently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. To inſiſt no more upon theſe few particulars.</p>
            <p>The next &amp; laſt <hi>two things</hi> he inſtances as arguments of their <hi>faithfalneſs, are rather negative then poſitive;</hi> &amp; therefore can conclude nothing for his purpoſe <hi>when they were baniſhed by</hi> Ferdinand <hi>&amp;</hi> Iſabel <hi>out of</hi> Spain,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:183674:24"/>
               <hi>they made no reſiſtance:</hi> ergo, <hi>they were faithful;</hi> how will this rightly follow? and <hi>when they were thence expelled;</hi> it <hi>was not for any unfaithfulneſs;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prove their fidelity is as good an argument as the former. If they had had opportunity and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient warning (though they were half a million) I do not much queſtion what they would have done. And <hi>for their praying</hi> (which he urgeth for an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their faithfulneſs) <hi>for the Commonwealths wherein they live;</hi> ſo perhaps they did when <hi>they ſent to the Prince of</hi> Babylon, <hi>to ſtir him up againſt Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; when they conſpired to fire the City of</hi> London; <hi>when they ſucked away the ſap of the Engliſh proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by their extortions; when they clipped and coyned money,</hi> and ſo rather ſpoiled this Commonwealth; Did they not then alſo pray for the proſperity of it?</p>
            <p>As for any <hi>cruelty which might be ſhewed toward them, when expelled out of</hi> Spain <hi>and</hi> Portugal; I take not upon me to be a patron of it; neither of that which might be exerciſed toward them, by our own n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, whilſt here reſiding. Many times they have been uſed moſt pittifully; but generally in all places, they might thank themſelves for it: their carriage (here eſpecially) was ſuch, as upon the leaſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the people would ſhew their hatred of it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for to meet with objections made againſt their faithfulneſs, the Rabbi endeavors to clear his Countrymen from <hi>three aſpaerſions uſually caſt upon them,</hi> viz. <hi>uſury, killing children,</hi> and <hi>ſeducing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to their Religion:</hi> I wiſh they were but aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that they might the ſooner be wiped off: but that will not be, by all the skill their Nation hath. Was not uſury with great extortion their continual practice <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> What it was in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> we have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183674:25"/>already ſeen; and that it is uſed by them in <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>What it was in</hi> France, <hi>ſee</hi> Baronius <hi>his</hi> Annal. ad ann. <hi>1198 1223. 1306.1348.</hi> Ingenti foenore cives ita ſibi oboerato; habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, ut eorum proediis ditatieim dias fere Civitates vendicarent, alios in cuſtadia penes ſe ſervarent, pleroſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fortunis omnitus, diſſolvendi cauſa debiti ſpoliatos, mendicis non diſſimiles efficerent, idem ad an. <hi>1198.</hi>
               </note> he himſelf confeſſeth. Their principles of Religion do not forbid it then to us; though amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Beſides he ſhould have done well to declare, what they do in <hi>Poland, Pruſsia</hi> and other places; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where they cannot have ſuch opportunity of trading.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How they have uſed Chriſtian children,</hi> enough and too much hath been ſhewn already; it is not good any more to ſtir that puddle.<note place="margin">Vide Socrat. <hi>i. 7 cap. 10.</hi> Krantzium <hi>lib. 10.</hi> Wandal. <hi>cap 18.</hi> Papir. Maſſon. <hi>lib. 3. pig. 335</hi> Vide Baronium in Annal. ad an. <hi>1198.1236.1252.1287.</hi> ibid. <hi>1305.1348.1410.</hi> Et Bzovium ad ann. <hi>1432.1475.1494.</hi>
               </note> Not only do our own Authors affirm this; but Forreign writers teſtifie the ſame alſo to have been done in divers places: whoſe authority to queſtion, more then that of <hi>Manana of the Chronicles</hi> of the <hi>Xantes,</hi> and others, vvhich he brings as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their faithfulneſs (to which particulars we have already anſwered) it's neither ingenuity nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie to do it.</p>
            <p>For <hi>their perſwading Chriſtians to their Religion;</hi> we know it to be the practice (as the ambition) of all parties, to draw as many as they can in ſafety unto them; nay many further venture, then ſtands with their ſafety. Novv for the Rabbi to perſwade us that this is not their deſire (eſpecially meeting vvith ſuch as may eaſily be dravvn aſide) he cannot but be convinced of its impoſſibility. This vvas the cauſe, for vvhich they were baniſhed <hi>Granada</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Iſabel; having ſeduced ſome Noblemen of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> Andaluzie; vvhich he confeſſeth. And for their dravving Chriſtians to their Religion, ſee the Rabbi himſelf in a Book publiſhed 1650 called, <hi>The hope of Iſrael,</hi> Sect. 17. Where he inſtanceth thoſe of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:183674:25"/>his Religion, vvho attempted to draw, even the then Pope; <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth Emperour, and <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, to <hi>Judaiſm.</hi> See alſo <hi>Sect.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third and laſt motive</hi> for their re-admiſſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Rabbi, is <hi>the Nobility of their ſtock. His modeſty in this, is the reaſon he inſiſts no more upon it it being alſo ſufficiently known to all Chriſtians.</hi> He might as well be even as modeſt in his other tvvo; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he leaves it to others, for that it is ſaid, <hi>Let another mans mouth praiſe thee, and not thine own;</hi> in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he might alſo better have left the other. For <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> is a greater thing then <hi>outward extraction;</hi> and to be commended <hi>for virtue,</hi> is a greater honor then for <hi>greatneſs of birth,</hi> ſeeing that <hi>virtus eſt vera nobilitas.</hi> Indeed they are the off ſpring of faithful <hi>Abralam;</hi> to them vvere committed the Oracles of God; of them (which is more their honour) as to the fleſh came <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but they have cut themſelves off, by their rebellion againſt him; they are fallen from the truth, and thereby have forfeited their former ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Yet it is the earneſt deſire of all Chriſtians, to have them engraffed again into the true ſtock (to which I cannot conceive their re-admiſſion hither can at all conduce) and then their company would be more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come becauſe over and above what would come in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcore of Chriſtian love, their principles would be the ſafer.</p>
            <p>Now by this time (by all that hath been ſaid in way of relation and anſwer) I hope the caſe in hand is not far from being cleared abundantly and that it may be ſeen what theſe motives amount to, which the Rabbi hath tendred to conſideration. We cannot but ſee that the Jews at all times have ſo, for the moſt part, behaved
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:183674:26"/>themſelves; as that they have miniſtred to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians occaſion of diſlike and prejudice; and that all the ſlaughters and maſſacres of them may be laid at their own doors. Here in <hi>England,</hi> they firſt begun to crucifie children and oppreſs the people; before they were injured, to ſpeak on, or moleſted; they ſpoiled the coyn in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond his days; and yet had the priviledge of burying in all places of their abode grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The firſt tumult we read of raiſed againſt them was at the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt; and that was occaſioned by themſelves, offering to come into the Kings houſe, notwithſtanding a proclamation to the contrary. And the occaſion of the tumult at <hi>Lin</hi> was, their endeavour to kill a Convert: their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous extortion at <hi>Stamford, York,</hi> and other places, drew upon them the inconveniences that followed. After this the people inraged, proſecute them as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional enemies; yet they leave not off their extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, make it their annual practice to crucifie children, conſpire againſt City and people, ſtill clip and ſpoil the coyn, as very earneſt to undo themſelves. The ſeveral Kings getting gain by the bad uſage of the ſubject, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take occaſion to fleece them for their miſcarriages, and make their Markets out of the contention raiſed betwixt them and the Natives.</p>
            <p>We ſee how they have behaved themſelves fince their expulſion: how miſchievous to this Nation, in particular they had almoſt been in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Lopez.</hi> We ſee how they have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by other Princes and States how theſe Princes that ſtill retain them, are more carried by their private profit, then the good of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who in all places are weary of them; and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:183674:26"/>how theſe States with whom they live, have particular reaſons and intereſts; and have that advantage, which we, by the ſmall number of Merchants, and want of conveniency of trading cannot obtain.</p>
            <p>I cannot blame them for ſo earneſtly deſiring their reduction. this Land is another Land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> a plentiful Land, and therefore very deſirable in this their long (and worſe then) <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage; but the laſt experience of our Anceſtors what gueſts they were, and the teſtimonies of other Nations, rather may make us rejoyce they are gone, then be glad to enjoy their company any further.</p>
            <p>Such is the antipathy in Engliſh hearts againſt theſe men; derived (with ſome memory of their qualities) from their Anceſtors, that though it be now more then 365 years ſince their expulſion, yet not at all doth it ſeem to moderate, or be abated; an ill ſign of their future agreement, if ever permitted to meet again. Their memory ſtill remains as a patern of miſchievous mindes, either apt to do, or fit to ſuffer any violence; the very name of a Jew ſerving this people as a perfect meaſure, either to notifie the height of impiety in the agent, or to ſound the depth and bottom of an abject worthleſs and forlorn condition in any patient. Better we cannot expreſs more cut-throat dealing then thus, <hi>None but a Jew would have done ſo;</hi> lower we cannot prize any one of moſt abject condition, then by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring him to a <hi>Jew.</hi> For ſo in common ſpeech men uſe to exaggerate enormous wrongs. <hi>This had been enough for a Jew to ſuffer,</hi> or, <hi>I would not have done ſo to a Jew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet further, we ſhall ſee there's more in this then ordinary, if we look back at what's ſaid, and turn over the writings of foreign Authors; for ſcarce in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:183674:27"/>any other Countrey hath there been (within ſo little time) ſo many enormities committed by them, as in this; ſuch oppoſition and implacable malice ſhewed by any againſt them, as by this people; from the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, to their expulſion. This ſeems to intimate a more then ordinary repugnancy to each other; or ſome greater opportunity they have in this Land to be wicked, then in other places. And can we conclude they have left their old qualities? their hatred againſt Chriſt, and them that worſhip him, their Gripings, Uſuries, and cruel Oppreſſions? May we not judge them to be the ſame as before? and if their actions be not ſo enormous as formerly, is it not for want of opportunity, more by reſtraint, then any change of nature?</p>
            <p>They were not indeed ſo much to be accuſed at firſt, when admitted into this Iſland, ſubmitting to the Laws (not concerning Religion) and acting according to common Rules and Orders; and ſo without doubt they might do again, till time and opportunity broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their malice, it might be too late to wiſh they had not been received. If they ſhould act ſuch horrid Tragedies over again, imbruing their hands in the blood of yong and tender infants (crucifying them in ſcorn and deriſion of our profeſſion) it might be eaſier to wiſh them gone, then honorable to exile them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their faithfulneſs</hi> is ſufficiently known, ſay what they will (however always to the true intereſt of this Nation) and if they ſhould for better terms, play falſe with the State, hold intelligence with the enemies thereof, counterfeit the Coyn, clip the Money, ſet the Cities on fire, would not a ſafe prevention have proved better, then a too late remedy? Theſe things have been practiſed, and ſo may again: we have ſmall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:183674:27"/>encouragement (if opportunity ſhould be had) to hope the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For their Religion:</hi> we have no grounds but to think them as conceited and ſtubborn in their Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as great enemies to Chriſt and Chriſtians as their Anceſtors: we hear of few that are really and unfeignedly converted. So far is their Reduction from affording any hope of their Converſion, as we may fear the great cauſe of their ſo earneſt deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, is their ambition to draw others to them. Since the time they have been bolder to return hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, its more then to be feared, they have made many Proſelytes; and that if they might with impunity ſhew themſelves, and had toleration of their Religion, and an open way of their Worſhip granted, hundreds, if not thouſands, would then appear, who now are veiled under the name of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now there is opportunity for perverters to ſtir, matter too much diſpoſed for them to work upon; ſuch and ſo many opinions amongſt us which have affinity with their Tenents, as, denying Chriſt in reality, though not in words (by taking away his Natures, Offices, and the Real Hiſtory of him) there are but few ſteps betwixt them and that wherein principally the Jews diſſent from us. What will not people now believe? to what will not this prevailing Scepticiſm bring them? placing Religion in notions, and the power thereof rather in being nothing (or any thing) then ſomething. Unto what an height are our Quakers and Ranters flown? who taking away, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all foundations, make their own fancies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded conceptions, originals and rules of truth; and ſo being once poyſoned, are impregnable. Its the policy of Satan to gild his pills, his Emiſſaries now adays re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:183674:28"/>things under another notion then that to which they naturally tend; and if the Jews ſhould at the firſt not entice formally to their own way, yet they too well know the meaning of that ſaying (the truth of which our Religion of late hath ſadly felt) <hi>Divide &amp; regnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What they would take as an advantage to ſeduce, the ſame would prove an obſtacle to their converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; truth having ſuch ſad entertainment in this world, as the Brats of her Enemy, if born near her, are always accounted to be her Progeny. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil where there is moſt of truth, is always more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, ſo alſo moſt buſie, and what he worketh of ill, and mixeth with it, that he makes an occaſion alſo to raiſe prejudice againſt to hide it, and conceal it. Our preſent diviſions would open the door to receive their harm; but rather ſhut it againſt any counſel or other means for their converſion. Though God knows them that are his, and will preſerve them that belong unto him; yet means are to be uſed to bring about the end: and man (not daring to pry into the ſecret counſel of God) is bound to take the moſt likely way to produce an effect deſirable.</p>
            <p>That the Jews converſion draws nigh, is a greater truth, then that their Reduction hither would be a means unto it. It is not probable that this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which hath now been blinde for above 1600 years, ſhould be reſtored to ſight by any but extraordinary power, by any work but one miraculous. Its a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is rather to be born at once, and whoſe converſion will be as the reſurrection from the dead. Yet there ſeems other work that is to be done firſt; it is not probable, that they who live under (at leaſt) the Turk and Pope, ſhould be converted before their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:183674:28"/>downfall. And if a Proteſtant people be to do this great thing by their enterconrſe (as ſome may imagine) then there are ſuch places where they inhabite already of which, though we may not be apt to count ſo well, as of our ſelves; yet at preſent, they are in a more fit condition to perform it.</p>
            <p>Some there are, who taking upon them to know that which was hidden from Chriſt himſelf as man, and the holy Angels, will point us out the year of the fall of Antichriſt, and the Jews converſion; divers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that next year, <hi>viz.</hi> 1656. will bring theſe things to paſs. But experience may teach us how to rely upon theſe predictions; ſome who have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the times already paſt, for theſe accompliſhments, being viſibly miſtaken: And what conſequence is there in the nature of the thing; that there ſhould be juſt ſo many years from the birth of Chriſt to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of theſe things, as were from the Creation to the deluge? Doth God<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty himſelf to numbers of years, and always act according to former preſidents? But, as nothing is more deceitfull then account of time; ſo alſo is it to be feared, that men are generally miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the true number of years from the birth of Chriſt; being miſled by him that was the Author of this Ae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a. It was 532. years, according to the vulgar computation, before men uſed this account, meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their times before that, from the <hi>building of</hi> Rome, <hi>the beginning of</hi> Auguſtus; <hi>by the Olympiads, Indictions of</hi> Conſtantine, <hi>the Aera of the Martyrs and others:</hi> ſo that <hi>Dionyſius the Monk,</hi> who firſt brought up this account, being deceived in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of time that then was paſt, is thought by the moſt learned Chronologers to have miſſed of the juſt and full number of years. Some ſay he accounted
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:183674:29"/>above twenty too ſhort; others finde four years to have been paſt over: Others conclude he miſſed two,<note place="margin">Florentius Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gornienſis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſerius in Annal <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſeph. Scalig. de emendat. remporum.</note> miſtaking the true diſtance of the birth of Chriſt from the battel at <hi>Actium.</hi> Now, if we add but two years more, the foundation of the former opinion is quite removed; this preſent year, <hi>viz.</hi> 1655. being the 1657. <hi>of our Lord;</hi> and ſo doubtleſs, at leaſt, is to be accounted.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if the Jews were here ſetled already, and the Nation had ſufficient experience of their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and good behaviour; there's none that I know, would be ſo cruel, as to deſire their expulſion: or if they were ſo diſtreſſed generally, as to give them enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment would amount to an act of charity; their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction might well move to commiſeration, and more: but ſeeing they are gone, and yet have left ſuch a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial behind them; ſeeing generally they flouriſh ſo, and live ſo happily in other places, I hope to have written thus much can ſhew no evil will towards them; but that one may ſafely wiſh (at leaſt) the good of ones native Countrey, and yet heartily deſire the real and full proſperity of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
